John C. Greene Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
John C. Greene Papers.
undated, 1952-2005.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Greene, John C.
5.5 linear feet.
John Colton Greene (b. 1917) was a Professor of History at the University of Connecticut from 1967 until his retirement twenty years later. His research interests included history of evolutionary ideas in Western thought, early American science, and the historical relations of science, religion, and world view.
MSS19960008
Biography
Born on 5 March 1917 in Indianapolis, Indiana, John Colton Greene grew up in Vermillion, South Dakota where he graduated from the local public school system in 1934. A year after completing a B. A. at the University of South Dakota in 1938, he took an M.A. in American History from Harvard University and then began work on his doctorate. Greene served in the U. S. Army during World War II. His wartime career lasted almost three years (September 1942-April 1946) and took him around the world via San Francisco, Tasmania, India, Iran, Palestine, and Italy. While stationed in Iran, Greene met Ellen Wiemann, a Red Cross nurse from Larchmont, New York. The two were married in Cairo in November 1945 and ultimately had three children, Ruth, Ned, and John.
After the war, Greene returned to Harvard to complete his Ph.D., which he finished in 1952. In 1948, he began teaching, first at the University of Chicago (1948-1952), and then at the University of Wisconsin (1952-1956), Iowa State University (1956-1962), the University of California at Berkeley (1962-1963), and at the University of Kansas (1963-1967). He came to the University of Connecticut in 1967 and remained there until his retirement twenty years later. After his wife's 1998 death from cancer, Greene moved from Storrs in 1999 to California where he currently resides.
Greene's research and writing focused on early American science, the rise and development of evolutionary ideas in Western thought, and the historical relations of science, religion, and world view. He published numerous essays, journal articles and reviews in addition to such monographs as The Death of Adam: Evolution and Its Impact on Western Thought(1959), Science, Ideology and World View: Essays in the History of evolutionary Ideas (1981), and American Science in the Age of Jefferson (1984). Greene was honored as a Fellow of the Society of Fellows, H arvard University (1941-1942); a Guggenheim Fellow (1966-1967); a Visiting Scholar at Corpus Christi College, Cambridge University (1974); and Visiting Historian, National Museum of History and Technology, Smithsonian Institution (1978). He was President of the History of Science Society from 1975 to 1977 and in 1985 received an honorary doctorate of Humane Letters from the University of South Dakota.
Scope and Content
The collection documents the professional activities and interests of John C. Greene, a noted historian of science. The papers cover the years between 1952, when Greene was thirty-five years old and finishing his Ph.D., until 1999, when he moved to California after thirty-one years in Storrs, Connecticut. The materials include correspondence to and from Greene on the professional study and practice of the history of science, subject files on both the discipline and personages involved therein, and a selection of Greene's published articles, reviews and delivered lectures. Also in the collection are reviews of Greene's work by others and unpublished manuscripts, both of which are found in Series III. Collectively, the papers illustrate the evolution of the professional history of science as an academic discipline in the second half of the twentieth century from the perspective of Greene, regarded as one of the foremost practitioners thereof. Highlighted are subjects that stem from Greene's own interests. These areas include: Greene's investigation of the development of evolutionary ideas in Western thought, his examination of early American science, and his consideration of the historical relations of science, religion, and world view. The collection also provides a detailed account of Green's own career as a scholar, offering a record of the evolution of his own ideas, interests, and professional contacts in the study of history. Particularly helpful are Greene's subject correspondence in Series II with the evolutionary biologist Ernst Mayr, the founder of the “modern” synthesis in his field, and the evolutionists Theodosius Dobzhansky and Walter Bock. Also of note is an extensive correspondence with Dr. James R. Moore, editor of History, Humanity, and Evolution: Essays for John C. Greene (1989).
Arrangement
Series I: Chronological Correspondence ( 1959-1999 ). Contains correspondence that Greene did not separate by subject but collected chronologically.
Series II: Subject Correspondence ( 1954-2005 ). Consists of communications that Greene grouped by subject.: Subject files, however, should not be viewed as comprehensive of Greene's correspondence with a given individual or about a specific topic under an assigned heading. Materials from a particular subject frequently are included not only in Series II, but in Series I as well. For instance, Greene maintained a subject file on his correspondence with the evolutionist Ernst Mayr. However, he also left examples of his letters with Mayr in what is now Series I. No attempt was made to rectify such discrepancies in the effort to follow Greene's own organization of his papers as closely as possible.
Series III: Writings and Lectures ( undated, 1952-1998 ). Comprises a selection of Greene's published articles, reviews, and elegies from 1954 to 1996, together with unpublished materials and occasional lectures delivered by the historian from 1953 to 1998. These materials are not exhaustive of the body of such work created by Greene, but include those examples that he chose to include in his papers. The organization of this series again follows Greene's original groupings, which are reflected in the subseries contained herein. However, certain changes have been made. Journal articles are organized here by chronology, in which order Greene did not necessarily keep them. Reviews use an alphabetical order by author, as Greene maintained them. However, they are prefixed by a small set of reviews dated between 1954 and 1996, which were found elsewhere among Greene's papers. Unpublished manuscripts—which are undated—were likewise found elsewhere in the collection. Occasional lectures follow Greene's original chronological filing, but have been separated into two categories: “general” and “Darwin.” This division has been made to draw focus upon Greene's work with Darwin and the theory of evolution, with which the historian is well-associated.
An additional aspect of Series III is the inclusion of reviews by other authors of five published books by Greene. These critiques, which directly follow Greene's own reviews, include both published materials and personal communications to Greene as he collected them under by the title of each book reviewed. The reviewed books in this subseries are American Science in the Age of Jefferson (1984), Darwin and the Modern World View (1961), Death of Adam (1959), Science, Ideology, and World View (1981), and The Science of Minerals in the Age of Jefferson (1979), which he co-wrote with John G. Burke.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut. Dept. of History.; Universities and colleges--Connecticut.; History--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Connecticut--Education--Universities and colleges.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Manuscripts
Occupations:
Historian of Science
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
John C. Greene donated the papers to the University of Connecticut in 1998 and 1999 in fulfillment of an agreement reached with University Archives in April 1991.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Chronological Correspondence, 1959-1999
  - 1959 November - December (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - 1960 January - June (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - 1960 June - December (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - 1961 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - 1962 January - December (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - 1963 January - June (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - 1963 July - December (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - 1964 July - April (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - 1964 May - July (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - 1964 August - December (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - 1965 January - June (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - 1965 July - September (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - 1965 October - December (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - 1966 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - 1966 April - June (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - 1966 July - December (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - 1967 January - March (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - 1967 April - May (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - 1967 June - December (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - 1968 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - 1969 January - September (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - 1969 October - December (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - 1970 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - 1971 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - 1972 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 25)
  - 1973 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - 1974 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 27)
  - 1975 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 28)
  - 1976 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 29)
  - 1977 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - 1977 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 31)
  - 1978 January - December (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - 1979 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 33)
  - 1979 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - 1980 January - July (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - 1980 August - December (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - 1981 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - 1981 July - August (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - 1981 September - December (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - 1982 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - 1982 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - 1983 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - 1983 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 43)
  - 1984 January - June (Box 2:, Folder 44)
  - 1984 July - December (Box 2:, Folder 45)
  - 1985 January - April (Box 2:, Folder 46)
  - 1985 May - August (Box 2:, Folder 47)
  - 1985 September - December (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - 1986 January - June (Box 3:, Folder 49)
  - 1986 July - December (Box 3:, Folder 50)
  - 1987 January - March (Box 3:, Folder 51)
  - 1987 April - July (Box 3:, Folder 52)
  - 1987 August - October (Box 3:, Folder 53)
  - 1987 November - December (Box 3:, Folder 54)
  - 1988 January - February (Box 3:, Folder 55)
  - 1988 March - April (Box 3:, Folder 56)
  - 1988 May - August (Box 3:, Folder 57)
  - 1988 September - December (Box 3:, Folder 58)
  - 1989 January - June (Box 3:, Folder 59)
  - 1989 July - December (Box 3:, Folder 60)
  - 1990 January - June (Box 3:, Folder 61)
  - 1990 July - December (Box 3:, Folder 62)
  - 1991 January - June (Box 3:, Folder 63)
  - 1991 July - December (Box 3:, Folder 64)
  - 1992 January - May (Box 3:, Folder 65)
  - 1992 June - August (Box 3:, Folder 66)
  - 1992 September - December (Box 3:, Folder 67)
  - 1993 January - December (Box 3:, Folder 68)
  - 1994 January - December (Box 3:, Folder 69)
  - 1995 January - Septmeber (Box 4:, Folder 70)
  - 1995 October - December (Box 4:, Folder 71)
  - 1996 January - March (Box 4:, Folder 72)
  - 1996 April - December (Box 4:, Folder 73)
  - 1997 January - June (Box 4:, Folder 74)
  - 1997 July - December (Box 4:, Folder 75)
  - 1998 January - December (Box 4:, Folder 76)
  - 1999 January (Box 4:, Folder 77)
- Series II: Subject Correspondence, 1954-2005
  - Allen, Garland, 1996-1998 (Box 5:, Folder 78)
  - American Philosophical Society, 1992-1994 (Box 5:, Folder 79)
  - American Science in the Age of Jefferson, 1984-1985 (Box 5:, Folder 80)
  - Ayala, Francisco J., 1999-2005 (Box 12:, Folder 193)
  - Blanckaert, Claude, 1990-1994 (Box 5:, Folder 81)
  - Bock, Walter, 1964-1999 (Box 5:, Folder 82)
  - Book of Essays, 1998 (Box 5:, Folder 83)
  - Buffon 98, 1987-1988 (Box 5:, Folder 84)
  - Darwin Correspondence Project, 1987-1997 (Box 5:, Folder 85)
  - De Beer, Gavin, 1969 (Box 5:, Folder 86)
  - Dobzhansky, Thomas, 1959-1999 (Box 5:, Folder 87)
  - Encyclopedia, 1992-1996 (Box 5:, Folder 88)
  - France, 1989-1996 (Box 5:, Folder 89)
  - Festschrift, 1987-1990 (Box 5:, Folder 90)
  - Gayon, Jean, 1990-1994 (Box 5:, Folder 91)
  - Ghiselin, Michael, 1996 (Box 5:, Folder 92)
  - History of American Science, 1969-1986 (Box 5:, Folder 93)
  - History of Geology, 1958-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 94)
  - History of Geology, 1973-1975 (Box 5:, Folder 95)
  - History of Geology, 1976-1977 (Box 6:, Folder 96)
  - History of Geology, 1978-1980 (Box 6:, Folder 97)
  - History of Geology, 1981-1989 (Box 6:, Folder 98)
  - International Society for the History, Philosophy, and Social Studies of Biology (ISHPSSB), 1992-1997 (Box 6:, Folder 99)
  - Journal of the History of Biology, 1987-1997 (Box 6:, Folder 100)
  - Junto Correspondence, 1960-1967 (Box 6:, Folder 101)
  - Kleinman, Kim, 1994-1997 (Box 6:, Folder 102)
  - Levin, Saul, 1994-1996 (Box 6:, Folder 103)
  - Lightman, Bernard, 1994-1997 (Box 6:, Folder 104)
  - Lyons, Sherrie, 1995-1997 (Box 6:, Folder 105)
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1960-1989 (Box 6:, Folder 106)
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1990-1994 (Box 6:, Folder 107)
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1995-1998 (Box 6:, Folder 108)
  - Mayr, Ernst, 1994-2003 (Box 12:, Folder 195)
  - Mayr Symposium, 1986-1994 (Box 7:, Folder 109)
  - Moore, Jim, 1974-1986 (Box 7:, Folder 110)
  - Moore, Jim, 1987-1988 (Box 7:, Folder 111)
  - Moore, Jim, 1989-1990 (Box 7:, Folder 112)
  - Moore, Jim, 1991-1992 (Box 7:, Folder 113)
  - Moore, Jim, 1993-1995 (Box 7:, Folder 114)
  - Moore, Jim, 1996-1999 (Box 7:, Folder 115)
  - Mount Vernon, 1992-1993 (Box 7:, Folder 116)
  - Nelson, Gareth, 1992-1994 (Box 7:, Folder 117)
  - O'Hear, Anthony, 2001-2004 (Box 12:, Folder 194)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1967-1974 (Box 7:, Folder 118)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1975-1979 (Box 7:, Folder 119)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1980-1981 (Box 8:, Folder 120)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1982-1984 (Box 8:, Folder 121)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1985-1987 (Box 8:, Folder 122)
  - Occasional Lectures, 1988-1989 (Box 8:, Folder 123)
  - O'Hara, Robert, 1990-1994 (Box 8:, Folder 124)
  - Personal, 1971-1995 (Box 8:, Folder 125)
  - Presses, 1958-1979 (Box 8:, Folder 126)
  - Presses, 1980-1989 (Box 8:, Folder 127)
  - Presses, 1990-1994 (Box 8:, Folder 128)
  - Presses, 1995-1996 (Box 8:, Folder 129)
  - Presses, 1997-1998 (Box 8:, Folder 130)
  - Reviews and Comments, 1962-1974 (Box 8:, Folder 131)
  - Reviews and Comments, 1975-1979 (Box 9:, Folder 132)
  - Reviews and Comments, 1980-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 133)
  - Richards, Bob, 1994 (Box 9:, Folder 134)
  - Roger, Jacques, 1985-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 135)
  - Ruse, Michael, 1994-1997 (Box 9:, Folder 136)
  - Ruse, Michael, 1998-1999 (Box 9:, Folder 137)
  - Smithsonian, 1989-1993 (Box 9:, Folder 138)
  - Smocovitis, Betty, 1992-1998 (Box 9:, Folder 139)
  - Spanagel, David, 1998 (Box 9:, Folder 140)
  - University of Connecticut Archives, 1991 (Box 9:, Folder 141)
  - Uppsala, 1989-1995 (Box 9:, Folder 142)
- Series III: Writings and Lectures, undated, 1952-1998
  - Subseries A: Journal Articles and Unpublished Manuscripts, n.d, 1954-1996
    - Journal Articles, 1954-1959 (Box 10:, Folder 143)
    - Journal Articles, 1960-1969 (Box 10:, Folder 144)
    - Journal Articles, 1970-1979 (Box 10:, Folder 145)
    - Journal Articles, 1980-1996 (Box 10:, Folder 146)
    - Unpublished Manuscripts, undated (Box 10:, Folder 147)
  - Subseries B: Reviews by Greene, 1957-1996
    - Reviews, 1957-1996 (Box 10:, Folder 148)
    - Appleman, Philip, 1971 (Box 10:, Folder 149)
    - Brooke, John Hedley, 1991 (Box 10:, Folder 150)
    - Bowler, Peter, 1984-1987 (Box 10:, Folder 151)
    - Cutright, Paul Russell, 1969 (Box 10:, Folder 152)
    - Daniels, George, 1968-1969 (Box 10:, Folder 153)
    - Dobzhansky, Theodosius, 1962 (Box 10:, Folder 154)
    - Ewan, Joseph ☀ Nesta, 1971 (Box 10:, Folder 155)
    - Fothergill, Phil, 1961-1963 (Box 10:, Folder 156)
    - Foucault, Michel, 1967 (Box 10:, Folder 157)
    - Gillespie, Neal, 1980 (Box 10:, Folder 158)
    - Gruber, Howard, and Paul Barrett, 1974 (Box 10:, Folder 159)
    - Goldman, Nathan, 1992 (Box 10:, Folder 160)
    - Haller, John, 1972 (Box 10:, Folder 161)
    - Houghton, Walter, 1977 (Box 10:, Folder 162)
    - Klein, Rudolph, 1988 (Box 10:, Folder 163)
    - Mayr, Ernst, 1992 (Box 10:, Folder 164)
    - Nitecki, Mathew, 1991 (Box 10:, Folder 165)
    - Numbers, Ronald, 1978 (Box 10:, Folder 166)
    - Porter, Charlotte, 1987 (Box 10:, Folder 167)
    - Prichard, James, 1975 (Box 10:, Folder 168)
    - Regis, Pamela, 1992 (Box 10:, Folder 169)
    - Richards, Robert, 1988 (Box 10:, Folder 170)
    - Ruse, Michael, 1980 (Box 10:, Folder 171)
    - Russell, Colin, 1987 (Box 10:, Folder 172)
    - Sanderson, Stephen, 1992 (Box 10:, Folder 173)
    - Wilson, Leonard, 1970-1973 (Box 10:, Folder 174)
  - Subseries C: Elegies, 1984-1989
    - Elegies, 1984-1989 (Box 10:, Folder 175)
  - Subseries D: Reviews of Greene's Works by Others, 1952-1995
    - American Science in the Age of Jefferson, 1984-1986 (Box 10:, Folder 176)
    - Darwin and the Modern World View, 1961-1974 (Box 10:, Folder 177)
    - Death of Adam, 1952-1995 (Box 10:, Folder 178)
    - Science, Ideology, and World View, 1981-1983 (Box 10:, Folder 179)
    - Science of Minerals in the Age of Jefferson, 1979-1982 (Box 10:, Folder 180)
  - Subseries E: Occasional Lectures, undated, 1953-1998
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1953-1960 (Box 11:, Folder 181)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1961-1970 (Box 11:, Folder 182)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1971-1980 (Box 11:, Folder 183)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1981-1984 (Box 11:, Folder 184)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1985-1988 (Box 11:, Folder 185)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, 1989-1994 (Box 11:, Folder 186)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, undated (Box 11:, Folder 187)
    - Occasional Lectures, General, undated (Box 11:, Folder 188)
    - Occasional Lectures, Darwin, Late 1950s-1980 (Box 11:, Folder 189)
    - Occasional Lectures, Darwin, 1981-1989 (Box 11:, Folder 190)
    - Occasional Lectures, Darwin, 1989-1998 (Box 11:, Folder 191)
    - Occasional Lectures, Darwin, undated (Box 11:, Folder 192)